Finding Aid for Gilbert Ross Papers 1911-1975
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gilbert Ross Papers 1911-1975
Ross, Gilbert, 1903-
5 linear feet
Professor of music at the University of Michigan, and founder and first violinist with the Stanley Quartet. Correspondence relating to music and musical performance and to his career at the University of Michigan; publications; photographs; scrapbooks containing clippings, programs, correspondence, and an occasional photograph; files relating to his violin performances and work with the Stanley Quartet.
85378 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Gilbert Ross (Donor No. 5720 ) in February 1976.
The collection is open for research.
Gilbert Ross was an internationally recognized violinist who served as professor of music and first violinist of the Stanley Quartet at the University of Michigan from 1942 until his retirement in 1970.
Born in Lincoln, Nebraska in 1903, Ross was raised in Madison, Wisconsin where his father was a faculty member at the University of Wisconsin. His early musical studies were at the Wisconsin School of Music and the Chicago Musical College. In 1917, at the age of 13, he was awarded the College's Diamond Medal for the Preparatory Department in recognition of his great talent. His principal violin instruction came under the great masters Leon Sametini in Chicago, and later under Leopold Auer in New York.
During the 1922-1923 season Ross toured Germany making his solo debut with the Berlin Philharmonic. Upon his return to the United States in 1923 he presented a debut recital at Town Hall in New York, and in 1925 he performed his London debut. During the coming years he appeared in concerts throughout the United States and Canada performing both as an orchestral soloist and in solo recitals.
Professor Ross' teaching experience began at Cornell University in 1931 as assistant professor of music. From 1935 to 1942 he served as associate professor of music at Smith College. He joined the faculty of the University of Michigan in 1942 where he remained until his retirement in 1970. In the summer of 1936, Ross taught at the University of Wisconsin and in the summer of 1960 he taught at Yale University.
While at the University of Michigan, Ross served as a strong proponent of revitalizing the string program and establishing a string quartet in residence. It was under Gilbert Ross' encouragement that the Stanley Quartet was established in 1949. The quartet was named by the Board of Regents in honor of Albert A. Stanley, a leader in the early musical life of Ann Arbor and professor and director of the School of Music from 1889 until his retirement in 1922. The Stanley Quartet was one of the earliest of the ensembles in residence established at schools of music in the United States.
Ross was a member of the quartet from its inception until his retirement in 1970. The membership of the quartet was very stable during Ross' tenure with the group. Gustave Rosseels of Brussels became second violinist in 1951, Robert Courte of Brussels became violist in 1957. Oliver Edel was the group's original cellist, replaced by Jerome Jelinek, a graduate of the University of Michigan, in 1961.
One of the primary functions of the Stanley Quartet was the presentation of new music. Annual commissions of chamber music began in 1949 with prominent composers of the twentieth century comprising the list. The Stanley Quartet gave first performances of over twenty-five works composed by such noteworthy composers as Walter Piston, Quincy Porter, Darius Milhaud, Elliot Carter, and George Crumb. In 1958, the quartet toured South America as part of the United States' International Cultural Program.
Ross' strong commitments to teaching and performance led to his being awarded the Outstanding Faculty Achievement Award in 1957. His dedication to promoting string instrument education and performance, both on an individual basis and through the Stanley Quartet, was a dominant force in building the string program at the University of Michigan School of Music.
The Gilbert Ross papers serve to document Ross' growth and development as a violinist, as well as the growth and development of the Stanley Quartet. With the exception of the alphabetical correspondence files the collection is in chronological order, wherever feasible. Some overlap of dates exists in the clippings files as well as the scrapbooks. The papers are arranged in eight series reflecting the various events and activities in Ross' life. These include: Correspondence, Teaching Career, Publications, Violin Performance, Stanley Quartet, Photographs, Scrapbooks and Notebooks, and Printed Music.
Subjects:
Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Musicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Stanley Quartet.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Music.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Musicians.; Smith College. String Quartet--1937.; Stanley Quartet.; University of Michigan. Symphony Orchestra--1943.; Violins.
Contributors:
Auer, Leopold, 1845-1930.; Bassett, Leslie, 1923-; Creston, Paul, 1906-1985; Crumb, George.; Finney, Ross Lee, 1906-1997; Haas, Karl.; Heifetz, Jascha, 1901-1987; Hermann, Emil.; Piston, Walter, 1894-1976.; Porter, Quincy, 1897-1966.; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968.; Szigeti, Joseph, 1892-1973.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence 1922-1971
  The Correspondence series, which spans the dates 1922-1971, offers much of musical interest. Included are letters from composers Paul Creston, George Crumb, Walter Piston, Quincy Porter and Ross Lee Finney. Extensive correspondence from violin master Leopold Auer as well as correspondence from violinists Jascha Heifitz and Joseph Szigeti and author Upton Sinclair is also included. The topics discussed in this series range from comments on premiere performances of several composer's works to violin performance practices. One folder contains correspondence with rare violin dealer Emil Hermann and documents Ross' purchase of the 1705 "Joset" Stradivarius violin. This folder serves to show how the violin market changed over a thirty-year time span.
  University of Michigan correspondence includes School of Music Dean Earl V. Moore from 1941 to 1964 and his successor James B. Wallace from 1950 to 1969. This correspondence provides insights into the music school's interest in the development of its string program and support of Ross. A consequent folder documents Ross' initial resignation submitted in 1964 and dissatisfaction with the music school's direction under Wallace's leadership. This resignation was eventually withdrawn by Ross.
  - A-D (Box 1)
  - E-H (Box 1)
  - J-L (Box 1)
  - M-P (Box 1)
  - S-Z (Box 1)
  - American String Teachers 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Allen P. Britton 1962-1971 (Box 1)
  - College Music Society 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Oliver Edel 1950-1960 (Box 1)
  - Emil Hermann 1924-1954 (Box 1)
  - Letters of Introduction 1938-1970 (Box 1)
  - Earl V. Moore 1941-1964 (Box 1)
  - James B. Wallace 1950-1969 (Box 1)
- Teaching Career
  The Teaching Career series has folders regarding Ross' appointments and resignations from Cornell University and Smith College. University of Michigan materials include correspondence concerning his academic appointment, resignation, and retirement. Also included are materials from various committees Ross served on and reports on music education written by Ross. In addition, one folder documents Ross' appointment at the University of Wisconsin, and two include his appointment at Yale as well as his ensemble course outlines.
  - Cornell University 1931, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Smith College 1935, 1943 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan
    - Academic appointment 1937-1970 (Box 1)
    - Committee correspondence 1944-1966 (Box 1)
    - Committee reports 1954 (Box 1)
    - School of Music committees 1962-1966 (Box 1)
    - Reports
      - Doctoral Programs in Musical Performance undated (Box 1)
      - Extra-Curricular Activities and Services 1946-1968 (Box 1)
      - String Instrument Teaching undated (Box 1)
    - Resignation 1956-1968 (Box 1)
    - Retirement 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Sabbaticals 1960-1966 (Box 1)
  - University of Wisconsin 1936 (Box 1)
  - Yale University
    - Summer Teaching Correspondence 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - Ensemble Course Notes, Summer 1960 (Box 1)
- Publications
  Included in the Publications series are articles written by Ross from 1937 to 1975 which, with the exception of one in Travel, appeared in music journals. The content of these articles relates to string instrument teaching.
  - "The Adequacy of Violin Instruction in High School" 1937 (Box 1)
  - "Teaching Stringed Instruments" Etude, March 1944 (Box 1)
  - "Teaching Stringed Instruments" Etude, April 1944 (Box 1)
  - "Which Edition of La Folia?" Repertoire, October 1951 (Box 1)
  - "The American Folk Tune in Contemporary Violin Music" Repertoire, November, 1951 (Box 1)
  - "Pergolisi via Strawinsky" Repertoire, January, 1952 (Box 1)
  - "Purpose of a String Quartet" 1953, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Notes, December 1955 (Box 1)
    reviewer
  - "Molawi-Portrait of a Lake" Travel, November, 1970 (Box 1)
  - "The Auer Mystique" Michigan Quarterly Review, Summer 1975 (Box 1)
  - "Creative Artists at Work" undated (Box 1)
- Violin Performance
  The Violin Performance series includes Performance and Repertory Lists and contains a thirty-two page listing of works performed by Ross in public concerts. This series also includes recital programs and clippings of reviews of Ross' performances prior to his arrival at the University of Michigan.
  - Performance and Repertory Lists (Box 1)
  - Recital Programs 1923-1956 (Box 1)
  - Clippings and Reviews
    - Germany 1922-1923 (Box 1)
    - 1923-1938 (Box 1)
    - 1923-1948 (Box 1)
- Stanley Quartet
  The Stanley Quartet material dates from 1942 to 1970 and includes Ross' initial proposal for the establishment of a quartet in residence as well as the Board of Regent's authorization for its establishment. Correspondence for the Stanley Quartet includes radio broadcaster Karl Haas and University of Michigan composer Leslie Bassett. The clippings and programs included document the quartet from its inception as well as a tour of South America taken in 1958 under the auspices of the International Cultural Program of the United States.
  - Brochures, Biographical Information (Box 2)
  - Founding: Proposals, Related Correspondence 1942-1966 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - 1949-1960 (Box 2)
    - 1961-1972 (Box 2)
    - South American Tour 1956-1960 (Box 2)
  - Annual Reports 1952/53-1969/70 (Box 2)
  - Repertoire Lists, Commissioned Works Lists 1949-1970 (Box 2)
  - Programs
    - 1949-1970 (Box 2)
    - South American Tour 1958 (Box 2)
  - Clippings
    - Founding 1949-1954 (Box 2)
    - 1949-1970 (Box 2)
    - South American Tour 1958 (Box 2)
    - Concert Reviews 1946-1968 (Box 2)
    - Record Reviews 1953-1960 (Box 2)
- Photographs
  Three folders of Photographs include photos of Ross ranging from the Chicago Musical College class in 1917, professional photos at various stages in Ross' career, and a series of more casual photos taken in 1958. The Stanley Quartet photographs include professional and rehearsal photos.
  - Gilbert Ross 1917-1963, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Stanley Quartet 1949-1968 (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks and Notebooks
  The Scrapbooks and Notebooks were compiled by Ross during his lifetime. Personal scrapbooks date from 1911 and include Ross' first performances as a child. They span the time until his earliest associations with the University of Michigan and contain programs, clippings, correspondence, and occasional photographs. The scrapbook dated 1925-1931 includes a letter from legendary violinist Leopold Auer. The Stanley Quartet scrapbooks are similar in content to the Ross scrapbooks focusing on programs, clippings, and correspondence. Binders containing programs dating from Ross' earliest performances at Smith College through his final performance with the Stanley Quartet in 1970 are labeled as to their contents and dates.
  - 1911-1922 (Box 2)
    photographs also included
  - 1922-1923 Germany (Box 2)
    much German language material
  - 1923-1928 (Box 3)
  - 1925-1931 (Box 3)
  - 1929-1936 (Box 3)
  - 1936-1940 Smith College (Box 3)
  - 1941-1946 Smith College, University of Michigan (Box 3)
  - Stanley Quartet Scrapbooks
    - 1946-1952 (Box 4)
    - 1953-1957 (Box 4)
    - 1957-1962 (Box 4)
    - 1962-1970 (Box 4)
    - 1968-1970 (Box 4)
  - Spiral Bound Notebook: programs of performances at Smith and Amherst 1935-1941 (Box 5)
  - Looseleaf Notebooks: Performances under auspices of University of Michigan
    - Solo recitals 1942-1967 (Box 5)
    - Orchestral soloist and conductor 1944-1968 (Box 5)
    - Stanley Quartet. 1949-1970, 3 notebooks (Box 5)
- Printed Music
  Printed Music in the Ross Collection primarily reflects his work in editing music for the violin. The editions included here, with the exception of orchestral arrangements, include the scores and parts.
  - Violin and Piano editions edited by Gilbert Ross
    - Boccherini: Concerto No.3 in G Major (Box 5)
    - Brahms: Intermezzo (Scotch Cradle Song) (Box 5)
    - Granados: Anoranza (Box 5)
    - Granados: La Maja y el Ruisenor (Box 5)
    - Mozart: Two Easy Minuets (Box 5)
    - Rameau: Dances from the Operas and Ballets (Box 5)
    - Scarlatti: Sonata (Box 5)
    - Schubert: Two Easy Minuets (Box 5)
    - Tartini: Concerto in D Major (Box 5)
  - Violin and Orchestra editions edited by Gilbert Ross
    - Tartini: Concerto in A Minor (Box 5)
    - Tartini: Concerto in F Major (Box 5)
  - Multiple Violin editions edited by Gilbert Ross
    - Reger: Folk Song, Op. 37, No. 2 (Box 5)